(Watch on www.dramacool.club Support Admin)
(شاهد على www.dramacool.club دعم الإدارة)
This letter
هذه الرسالة
is the distress letter Consort Virtue wrote to Wei Yan years ago.
هي رسالة الاستغاثة التي كتبتها كونسورت فيرتو إلى وي يان قبل سنوات.
Wei Yan, for his own selfish desires,
وي يان، بدافع رغباته الأنانية،
returned to the Capital without orders.
عاد إلى العاصمة بدون أوامر.
He abandoned the soldiers of Jinzhou at the front line,
تخلى عن جنود جينتشو على خط المواجهة،
and ultimately
وفي نهاية المطاف
caused a catastrophe.
تسبب في كارثة.
[Yan, I hope this letter finds you well. [Disaster has struck, and I seek your help.]
[يان، أتمنى أن تصلك هذه الرسالة وأنت بخير. [لقد حلت كارثة، وأطلب مساعدتك.]
[Beijue has invaded our Great Yin. [My father led the troops]
[لقد غزا بيجوي يين العظيم. [قاد والدي القوات]
[to protect the peace of our court. [But it was all the schemes of traitors.]
[لحماية سلامة بلاطنا. [لكنها كانت جميعها مكائد الخونة.]
[They conspired and slandered, and that foolish ruler easily believed them.]
[لقد تآمروا وافتروا، وصدقهم ذلك الحاكم الأحمق بسهولة.]
A thief crying "thief".
لص يصرخ "لص".
Wei Yan,
وي يان,
you are the biggest traitor in the Battle of Jinzhou!
أنت أكبر خائن في معركة جينتشو!
This is Qi Rongyin's letter.
هذه رسالة تشي رونغين.
It's been 17 years.
لقد مرّت 17 سنة.
You must have forgotten.
لا بد أنك نسيت.
Let me read it for you.
دعني أقرأها لك.
Yan.
نعم.
- May this letter remind you of me. - Shut up!
- لعل هذه الرسالة تذكرك بي. - اصمت!
Wei Changyu, if you want a fight, let's fight.
وي تشانغيو، إذا كنت تريد قتالاً، فلنتقاتل.
Don't insult the innocence of the deceased.
لا تهينوا براءة المتوفى.
Prime Minister Wei, it seems there are still people you care about.
رئيس الوزراء وي، يبدو أن هناك أشخاصاً ما زلت تهتم لأمرهم.
Seventeen years ago,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً،
my mother hid this letter
أخفت أمي هذه الرسالة
inside the candy box you gave her.
داخل علبة الحلوى التي أعطيتها إياها.
All these years,
طوال هذه السنوات،
you've done too much evil.
لقد ارتكبت الكثير من الشر.
That's why you felt so guilty
لهذا السبب شعرت بالذنب الشديد
and didn't dare touch the candy box at all.
ولم يجرؤ على لمس علبة الحلوى على الإطلاق.
Prime Minister Wei, dare I ask you,
رئيس الوزراء وي، هل لي أن أسألك؟
in the past 17 years,
خلال السنوات الـ 17 الماضية،
have you ever repented to my father?
هل سبق لك أن تبت إلى أبي؟
Have you ever pitied
هل شعرت بالشفقة يوماً ما؟
the thousands of dead soldiers?
آلاف الجنود القتلى؟
Have you ever mourned
هل سبق لك أن حزنت؟
your sister who was forced to commit suicide?
أختك التي أُجبرت على الانتحار؟
A fake letter,
رسالة مزيفة،
a pair of fake Tiger Tally,
زوج من شرائط النمر المزيفة،
and you want to smear me?
وتريد أن تشوه سمعتي؟
Haven't you silenced enough people
ألم تسكتوا ما يكفي من الناس؟
because of this letter?
بسبب هذه الرسالة؟
If Consort Virtue knew in the afterlife
لو علمت قرينة الفضيلة في الآخرة
- the things you've done... - Shut up!
- الأشياء التي فعلتها... - اصمت!
Don't mention her.
لا تذكر اسمها.
It's not hard to prove if the Tiger Tally
ليس من الصعب إثبات ما إذا كان إحصاء النمور
is real.
حقيقي.
The Tiger Tally is a treasure of the state,
يُعدّ سجلّ النمور كنزاً من كنوز الولاية.
archived in the Ministry of War.
مؤرشفة في وزارة الحرب.
Although the archives were burned,
على الرغم من حرق الأرشيفات،
the person who made the Tiger Tally back then,
الشخص الذي قام بإحصاء النمور آنذاك،
Grand Tutor Tao, is still alive.
المعلم الأكبر تاو لا يزال على قيد الحياة.
Prime Minister Wei, you just need to ask him.
رئيس الوزراء وي، كل ما عليك فعله هو أن تسأله.
Grand Tutor Tao has arrived.
لقد وصل المعلم الأكبر تاو.
Greetings, Your Majesty.
تحية طيبة يا صاحب الجلالة.
Rise.
يعلو.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
شكراً لك يا صاحب الجلالة.
Grand Tutor Tao is one of the few witnesses from that time.
المعلم الأكبر تاو هو أحد الشهود القلائل من ذلك الوقت.
We must preserve the Royal Family's dignity.
يجب علينا الحفاظ على كرامة العائلة المالكة.
As such, please determine if this
لذا، يرجى تحديد ما إذا كان هذا
military tally is genuine or not.
هل الإحصاءات العسكرية صحيحة أم لا؟
Yes, Your Majesty.
نعم يا جلالة الملك.
[Talisman of Military Field]
[تميمة الميدان العسكري]
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
I personally supervised the making of this tally back then.
لقد أشرفت شخصياً على إعداد هذا الإحصاء في ذلك الوقت.
There is a mark on it.
توجد علامة عليه.
This is the real item.
هذا هو المنتج الأصلي.
Prime Minister Wei,
رئيس الوزراء وي
what else do you have to say?
ماذا لديك لتقوله أيضاً؟
You will be Empress soon.
ستصبحين إمبراطورة قريباً.
Wei Yan!
وي يان!
You are ambitious, cruel,
أنت طموح، قاسٍ،
and have deceived your ruler.
وقد خدعتم حاكمكم.
Your crimes deserve death!
جرائمك تستحق الموت!
Imperial Guard!
الحرس الإمبراطوري!
Here.
هنا.
Take him down.
اقضِ عليه.
Yes.
نعم.
Wei Yan, you...
وي يان، أنت...
Kid of the Qi family,
طفل عائلة تشي،
do you have the guts?
هل لديك الشجاعة؟
Yigui, you cannot make more mistakes.
يا ييغي، لا يمكنك ارتكاب المزيد من الأخطاء.
Report!
تقرير!
Your Majesty, bad news.
جلالة الملك، لدي أخبار سيئة.
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[مجتهد وفاضل]
The rebel Sui Yuanhuai
المتمرد سوي يوانهواي
has sent his army to breach the Great Yin Gate.
أرسل جيشه لاختراق بوابة يين العظيمة.
What?
ماذا؟
How did they get in?
كيف دخلوا؟
The day has finally come.
لقد حان اليوم أخيراً.
He certainly knows how to pick a day.
إنه بالتأكيد يعرف كيف يختار اليوم المناسب.
The grievance between us, uncle and nephew,
الخلاف بيننا، أنا وعمّي وابن أخيّ،
must be settled.
يجب تسوية الأمر.
But before that,
لكن قبل ذلك،
I must quell this rebellion first.
يجب عليّ إخماد هذا التمرد أولاً.
Let's go.
دعنا نذهب.
[Pursuit of Jade]
[السعي وراء اليشم]
[Episode 39]
[الحلقة 39]
Everyone,
الجميع،
kill them!
اقتلهم!
[Great Yin Gate]
[بوابة يين العظيمة]
Welcome the rightful owner back to the palace.
أهلاً بالمالك الشرعي العائد إلى القصر.
After 17 years,
بعد 17 عاماً،
I have finally reclaimed my rightful place.
لقد استعدت مكاني الذي أستحقه أخيراً.
Your Highness regaining the throne
صاحب السمو يستعيد العرش
is clearly the will of Heaven.
من الواضح أن هذه هي إرادة السماء.
It is your destiny.
هذا قدرك.
Qianqian.
تشيان تشيان.
Well?
حسنًا؟
I have kept
لقد احتفظت
my promise to you.
هذا وعدي لك.
You madman.
يا مجنون.
Do you really think I want to be your Empress?
هل تعتقد حقاً أنني أريد أن أكون إمبراطورتك؟
Keep dreaming.
استمر في الحلم.
You will agree.
ستوافق.
Brother Sheng.
الأخ شينغ.
You've sat on this throne for over a decade.
لقد جلست على هذا العرش لأكثر من عقد من الزمان.
Was it comfortable?
هل كان مريحاً؟
Brother.
أخ.
I...
أنا...
I have been waiting for you for a long time.
لقد كنت أنتظرك منذ وقت طويل.
The Imperial Seal is here.
الختم الإمبراطوري هنا.
It's all yours.
كل شيء لك.
Please don't kill me, Brother.
أرجوك لا تقتلني يا أخي.
Brother, don't kill me.
يا أخي، لا تقتلني.
To think Great Yin has a pushover like you as the emperor...
يا للعجب! أن يكون الإمبراطور العظيم يين ضعيف الشخصية مثلك...
How can you live up to the torture I've suffered all these years?
كيف يمكنك أن ترقى إلى مستوى التعذيب الذي عانيت منه طوال هذه السنوات؟
Take him away.
خذوه بعيداً.
Await my judgment.
انتظروا حكمي.
Yes.
نعم.
Don't kill me.
لا تقتلني.
Is he really going to be the Emperor?
هل سيصبح الإمبراطور حقاً؟
Report! Unusual movements spotted at Xuan Gate.
تقرير! رُصدت تحركات غير عادية عند بوابة شوان.
Reinforcements may be arriving from outside the palace.
قد تصل التعزيزات من خارج القصر.
Not good.
ليس جيدا.
It's a trap.
إنه فخ.
Li Xing colluded with the rebel Sui Yuanhuai to commit treason.
تواطأ لي شينغ مع المتمرد سوي يوانهواي لارتكاب الخيانة.
Such traitors
هؤلاء الخونة
must all be arrested.
يجب القبض عليهم جميعاً.
Old Wretch Wei.
العجوز البائس واي.
Do not think
لا تفكر
that with just these few men,
ذلك مع هؤلاء الرجال القلائل فقط،
you can stop His Highness's Fifth Barracks.
بإمكانك إيقاف الثكنات الخامسة لصاحب السمو.
Is this not enough?
أليس هذا كافياً؟
Just these few men?
هؤلاء الرجال القلائل فقط؟
Besides, it's not yet certain whose side
إلى جانب ذلك، لم يتضح بعد أي جانب
Marquis of Wu'an is on.
ماركيز ووآن يُعرض الآن.
Marquis of Wu'an, since you've come to join the fun,
ماركيز ووآن، بما أنك أتيت لتنضم إلى المرح،
why not cooperate with me?
لماذا لا تتعاون معي؟
I have already detained that puppet emperor.
لقد احتجزت ذلك الإمبراطور الدمية بالفعل.
Why not serve me?
لماذا لا تخدمني؟
After all, I am the true blood of Crown Prince Chengde.
فأنا في النهاية من سلالة ولي العهد تشنغده الحقيقية.
Qi Min.
تشي مين.
You secretly colluded with Beijue
لقد تواطأت سرًا مع بيجوي
and intended to use this chance to threaten Great Yin.
وكان ينوي استغلال هذه الفرصة لتهديد يين العظيم.
Did you really think I was unaware?
هل ظننت حقاً أنني كنت غافلاً؟
Ever since you claimed to be the heir of Crown Prince Chengde,
منذ أن ادعيت أنك وريث ولي العهد تشنغده،
you have forgotten the former Eastern Palace's
لقد نسيتم القصر الشرقي السابق
bravery in swearing death rather than surrendering to Beijue.
شجاعة في التعهد بالموت بدلاً من الاستسلام لبيجو.
How could I, Xie Zheng,
كيف لي أن أفعل ذلك يا شيه تشنغ؟
ever submit to you?
هل سبق لأحد أن خضع لك؟
What?
ماذا؟
You dare to collude with Beijue in secret
أتجرؤ على التواطؤ مع بيجوي سراً؟
and hand over Great Yin's territory to barbarians?
وتسليم أراضي يين العظيم للبرابرة؟
There is no turning back now.
لا رجعة الآن.
Grand Tutor Li, it is too late for regrets.
المعلم الكبير لي، لقد فات الأوان على الندم.
You...
أنت...
What Prime Minister Wei has done is far worse than what I have done.
ما فعله رئيس الوزراء وي أسوأ بكثير مما فعلته أنا.
The fall of Jinzhou,
سقوط جينتشو،
the slaughter of its citizens,
مذبحة مواطنيها،
and the cession of the 12 commanderies of Liaodong to the barbarians
والتنازل عن المقاطعات الاثنتي عشرة في لياودونغ للبرابرة
were all caused by Wei Yan
كل ذلك كان بسبب وي يان
in his desire to seize control of Great Yin.
في رغبته في السيطرة على يين العظيم.
I am merely completing the game
أنا فقط أقوم بإكمال اللعبة
that he left unfinished years ago.
أنه تركها غير مكتملة منذ سنوات.
You...
أنت...
Prime Minister Wei.
رئيس الوزراء وي.
Seventeen years ago,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً،
you bathed the palace in blood.
لقد غمرت القصر بالدماء.
Did you think that no one would know
هل ظننت أن لا أحد سيعرف؟
about your illicit affairs in the palace that way?
بخصوص علاقاتك غير المشروعة في القصر بهذه الطريقة؟
You're just a bastard posing as royalty.
أنت مجرد وغد يتظاهر بأنه من العائلة المالكة.
How dare you spout nonsense and fabricate facts?
كيف تجرؤ على التفوّه بالهراء وتلفيق الحقائق؟
You know better than anyone
أنت أعلم من أي شخص آخر
who is spouting the nonsense here.
من الذي ينشر هذا الهراء هنا؟
Seize him.
اقبضوا عليه.
All the traitors and rebels present today
جميع الخونة والمتمردين الحاضرين اليوم
shall be executed without mercy.
سيتم إعدامه بلا رحمة.
Look, Prime Minister Wei.
انظر يا رئيس الوزراء وي.
Your wife and son are here.
زوجتك وابنك هنا.
I assure you,
أؤكد لك،
if your men dare to step forward,
إذا تجرأ رجالكم على التقدم،
their heads will roll.
ستُقطع رؤوسهم.
I did not expect you to be so cold-blooded.
لم أتوقع منك أن تكون بهذه القسوة.
Then let Madam Wei
ثم دع السيدة وي
and the Young Master
والسيد الشاب
go to hell first.
اذهب إلى الجحيم أولاً.
Kill them!
اقتلهم!
Kill!
قتل!
Don't kill me.
لا تقتلني.
I will make you Great Generals, alright?
سأجعلكم قادة عظماء، حسناً؟
Alright?
على ما يرام؟
One more word and you're dead, you dog of an Emperor!
كلمة أخرى وستكون ميتاً، أيها الإمبراطور الحقير!
It's time to end this.
حان الوقت لإنهاء هذا.
Prime Minister.
رئيس الوزراء.
This is between us, uncle and nephew.
هذا سر بيننا، أنا وعمّي وابن أخيّ.
Stay out of it. Stand down.
ابتعد عن الأمر. تراجع.
♪ The world is vast ♪
♪ العالم واسع ♪
♪ The storm is rising ♪
♪ العاصفة تتصاعد ♪
♪ Day and night ♪
♪ ليلاً ونهاراً ♪
♪ We strive to save the world ♪
♪ نسعى جاهدين لإنقاذ العالم ♪
Your swordsmanship has improved quite a bit.
لقد تحسنت مهاراتك في المبارزة بالسيف بشكل ملحوظ.
♪ All people ♪
♪ جميع الناس ♪
I will use my father's swordsmanship
سأستخدم مهارات والدي في المبارزة
to seek justice for my and Changyu's parents,
السعي لتحقيق العدالة لوالديّ ووالديّ تشانغيو،
♪ Are part of the past ♪
♪ جزء من الماضي ♪
the former Eastern Palace, and the soldiers who died tragically
القصر الشرقي السابق، والجنود الذين لقوا حتفهم بشكل مأساوي
in Jinzhou.
في جينتشو.
Very well.
جيد جدا.
♪ What's the date today? ♪
♪ ما هو تاريخ اليوم؟ ♪
Come on.
تعال.
♪ How lamentable ♪
♪ يا للأسف ♪
♪ The world is vast ♪
♪ العالم واسع ♪
Give up.
يستسلم.
You will never get.
لن تحصل على ذلك أبداً.
♪ The storm is rising ♪
♪ العاصفة تتصاعد ♪
what doesn't belong to you.
ما لا يخصك.
Look, this empire belongs to me.
انظروا، هذه الإمبراطورية ملكي.
♪ Day and night ♪
♪ ليلاً ونهاراً ♪
It was mine from the start!
كان ملكي منذ البداية!
♪ We strive to save the world ♪
♪ نسعى جاهدين لإنقاذ العالم ♪
Do you like it?
هل أحببت ذلك؟
Do you?
هل أنت؟
I don't want any of it.
لا أريد أيًا من ذلك.
♪ All people ♪
♪ جميع الناس ♪
Being an emperor is hard.
أن تكون إمبراطوراً أمر صعب.
♪ Are part of the past ♪
♪ جزء من الماضي ♪
♪ What's the date today? ♪
♪ ما هو تاريخ اليوم؟ ♪
I don't want to be an emperor anymore.
لا أريد أن أكون إمبراطوراً بعد الآن.
♪ How lamentable ♪
♪ يا للأسف ♪
I won't do it anymore.
لن أفعل ذلك بعد الآن.
You really are mad!
أنت مجنون حقاً!
I am not mad.
أنا لست غاضباً.
I chose to live because of you.
اخترتُ أن أعيش بفضلك.
For me?
لي؟
Fine.
بخير.
If I die, you'll stop being mad.
إذا مت، ستتوقف عن الغضب.
I will not allow you to die.
لن أسمح لك بالموت.
Qi Min!
تشي مين!
Let go of Qianqian.
اتركي تشيان تشيان.
Changyu.
تشانغيو.
Don't worry about me.
لا تقلق عليّ.
I can't escape.
لا أستطيع الهروب.
Let go of her!
اتركها!
Or I'll kill you.
وإلا سأقتلك.
Changyu.
تشانغيو.
Just let go.
دع الأمر يمر.
My matter with him shouldn't drag you down.
لا ينبغي أن تؤثر مشكلتي معه عليك سلباً.
I wanted imperial power.
كنت أرغب في السلطة الإمبراطورية.
And I wanted you.
وكنت أريدك.
But in the end,
لكن في النهاية،
I have nothing.
ليس لدي أي شيء.
Let go!
اتركه!
You'll kill her!
ستقتلها!
He won't let go.
لن يتركها.
He will never learn to let go.
لن يتعلم أبداً كيف يتخلى.
♪ I just don't want to ♪
♪ لا أريد ذلك ♪
♪ Keep weighing every word ♪
♪ تأمل كل كلمة جيداً ♪
♪ And hiding in time in silence ♪
♪ والاختباء في الزمن في صمت ♪
♪ It's not that I don't believe in karma ♪
♪ ليس الأمر أنني لا أؤمن بالكارما ♪
♪ That I'm being stubborn ♪
♪ أنني عنيد ♪
You're selfish,
أنت أناني،
♪ Some endings have long been ♪
♪ بعض النهايات كانت منذ زمن طويل ♪
cruel,
فظ،
and unpredictable.
وغير متوقع.
♪ Weathered through a thousand years ♪
♪ صمدت عبر ألف عام ♪
But all of this is your disguise.
لكن كل هذا مجرد تمويه منك.
♪ Traced by those who come after ♪
♪ تتبعها الأجيال اللاحقة ♪
You're just hiding your fear.
أنت فقط تخفي خوفك.
♪ Compared to fading away in sorrow ♪
♪ مقارنةً بالتلاشي في الحزن ♪
♪ I'd rather fight ♪
♪ أفضل القتال ♪
You are a pitiful person.
أنت شخص مثير للشفقة.
Is my love so worthless.
هل حبي عديم القيمة إلى هذه الدرجة؟
♪ Life's bitterness ♪
♪ مرارة الحياة ♪
that you can just trample on it?
هل يمكنك ببساطة أن تدوس عليه؟
♪ Comes from love ♪
♪ ينبع من الحب ♪
That isn't love.
هذا ليس حباً.
It's possession. It's control!
إنها ملكية. إنها سيطرة!
♪ Love, yet so hard to hold ♪
♪ الحب، ومع ذلك يصعب الحفاظ عليه ♪
I don't want anything.
لا أريد شيئاً.
♪ Like holding a torch in the wilderness ♪
♪ كحمل شعلة في البرية ♪
I just want to leave you forever.
أريد فقط أن أتركك إلى الأبد.
♪ Time sings a mournful song ♪
♪ الزمن يغني أغنية حزينة ♪
♪ Gathered little yet parted often ♪
♪ اجتمعوا قليلاً لكنهم افترقوا كثيراً ♪
For you,
لك،
♪ Just as tears fall into the long river ♪
♪ تمامًا كما تسقط الدموع في النهر الطويل ♪
I'm willing to learn it once.
أنا على استعداد لتعلمها مرة واحدة.
♪ I must dive into the starry stream ♪
♪ يجب أن أغوص في تيار النجوم ♪
♪ Don't mind me ♪
♪ لا تهتم بي ♪
♪ Everything has happened ♪
♪ كل شيء قد حدث ♪
♪ A thousand years from now no one's blood will remain warm ♪
♪ بعد ألف عام من الآن، لن يبقى دم أحد دافئاً ♪
♪ Let them laugh and mock ♪
♪ دعهم يضحكون ويسخرون ♪
♪ As long as you remember me ♪
♪ طالما أنك تتذكرني ♪
♪ Forget about ♪
♪ انسَ الأمر ♪
♪ Leaving a name in history ♪
♪ ترك بصمة في التاريخ ♪
♪ I only want to leave a mark in your life ♪
♪ أريد فقط أن أترك بصمة في حياتك ♪
♪ I will let go ♪
♪ سأترك الأمر ♪
♪ After taking this one last gamble ♪
♪ بعد القيام بهذه المجازفة الأخيرة ♪
♪ Forget about ♪
♪ انسَ الأمر ♪
♪ The carved stones or constellations ♪
♪ الأحجار المنحوتة أو الأبراج ♪
♪ I'll cast all karma behind me ♪
♪ سأتخلص من كل الكارما ♪
♪ Beacon fires stir the lords ♪
♪ نيران المنارات تُثير السادة ♪
♪ Unstoppable, ruthless fate ♪
♪ قدر لا يرحم ولا يمكن إيقافه ♪
Xuan!
شوان!
This arrow
هذا السهم
is to repay you for saving my mother.
هذا لأرد لك الجميل لإنقاذك والدتي.
Xuan!
شوان!
My father
والدي
is not a bastard like you.
ليس وغداً مثلك.
Xuan!
شوان!
[Xie]
[شيه]
The Jizhou and Xie Armies have arrived.
وصل جيشا جيتشو وشيه.
The palace is secure.
القصر آمن.
Soldiers who followed Qi and Wei in rebellion,
الجنود الذين تبعوا تشي ووي في التمرد،
listen to me.
استمع لي.
Those who lay down their arms and surrender
أولئك الذين يلقون أسلحتهم ويستسلمون
will be spared.
سيتم النجاة.
Those who resist
أولئك الذين يقاومون
will be charged with treason,
سيُتهم بالخيانة العظمى.
and their entire families executed.
وأُعدمت عائلاتهم بأكملها.
Prime Minister,
رئيس الوزراء،
you have been utterly defeated.
لقد هُزمت هزيمة نكراء.
Do you still intend to struggle?
هل ما زلت تنوي الكفاح؟
Jiuheng.
جيوهينج.
You really didn't disappoint me.
لم تخيب ظني أبداً.
Prime Minister!
رئيس الوزراء!
Let's retreat.
فلنتراجع.
We'll get you out of here.
سنخرجك من هنا.
No need.
لا حاجة.
A defeat
هزيمة
is a defeat.
إنها هزيمة.
When I chose this path of no return 17 years ago,
عندما اخترت هذا الطريق الذي لا رجعة فيه قبل 17 عاماً،
today's outcome
نتيجة اليوم
was already destined.
كان مقدراً له ذلك.
Take him away.
خذوه بعيداً.
Let's go, Prime Minister.
هيا بنا يا رئيس الوزراء.
It's over.
انتهى.
All of this
كل هذا
is finally over.
انتهى الأمر أخيراً.
It's over.
انتهى.
♪ In gold-thread dress, with moth or willow ornaments ♪
♪ في ثوب مطرز بخيوط ذهبية، مزين بزخارف على شكل فراشة أو صفصاف ♪
Our lives will be better from now on.
ستكون حياتنا أفضل من الآن فصاعدًا.
If there is a next life,
إذا كانت هناك حياة أخرى،
I'll pick you up instead.
سأصطحبك بدلاً من ذلك.
♪ Giggling, she melts into the throng with trails of scents ♪
♪ وهي تضحك، تندمج في الحشد تاركةً وراءها آثاراً من العطور ♪
♪ But in the crowd once and again I look for her in vain ♪
♪ لكنني أبحث عنها عبثاً وسط الزحام ♪
♪ When all at once I turn my head ♪
♪ عندما ألتفت فجأة ♪
♪ I find her there ♪
♪ أجدها هناك ♪
♪ Where lantern light is dimly shed ♪
♪ حيث ينبعث ضوء الفانوس بشكل خافت ♪
[Three days later]
[بعد ثلاثة أيام]
My Lord,
يا سيدي،
Madam Wei is here.
السيدة وي هنا.
Madam,
سيدتي،
please.
لو سمحت.
Aunt.
عمة.
Zheng.
تشنغ.
What are you doing? Please get up.
ماذا تفعل؟ من فضلك انهض.
Zheng,
تشنغ،
I want to beg you
أريد أن أتوسل إليك
to spare the Prime Minister's life.
لإنقاذ حياة رئيس الوزراء.
Sit down first.
اجلس أولاً.
Aunt,
عمة،
he didn't even care about the lives of you and your son.
لم يكن يهتم حتى بحياتك أنت وابنك.
Why plead for him?
لماذا نتوسل من أجله؟
Besides, the law will not permit it.
فضلاً عن ذلك، فإن القانون لن يسمح بذلك.
The Prime Minister is not irredeemable.
رئيس الوزراء ليس ميؤوساً منه.
If not for him,
لولا وجوده،
Xuan and I
أنا وشوان
would have died long ago.
كان سيموت منذ زمن بعيد.
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
Xuan's father
والد شوان
was the Prime Minister's subordinate.
كان تابعاً لرئيس الوزراء.
We pledged our lives to each other in secret.
لقد تعهدنا لبعضنا البعض بحياتنا سراً.
But he died in battle.
لكنه مات في المعركة.
My family
عائلتي
wanted to drown me in a pig cage.
أرادوا إغراقني في قفص خنازير.
It was the Prime Minister who saved me.
لقد أنقذني رئيس الوزراء.
He said.
قال.
Xuan's father was his former subordinate.
كان والد شوان مرؤوسه السابق.
He had no plans to marry in this life,
لم يكن لديه أي خطط للزواج في هذه الحياة،
but his family was pressuring him.
لكن عائلته كانت تضغط عليه.
Meanwhile, my unborn child and I
في هذه الأثناء، أنا وطفلي الذي لم يولد بعد
had nowhere else to turn to.
لم يكن لديه مكان آخر يلجأ إليه.
He said it was a win-win solution.
وقال إنها حل يرضي جميع الأطراف.
To us,
لنا،
he is our saviour.
هو منقذنا.
Zheng.
تشنغ.
I beg you, for the sake of Xuan
أرجوكم، من أجل شوان
taking an arrow for you,
أتلقى سهماً من أجلك،
please spare the Prime Minister's life.
أرجوكم ارحموا رئيس الوزراء.
Aunt.
عمة.
Did he remain unmarried
هل بقي عازباً؟
for Consort Virtue, Lady Qi?
من أجل فضائل القرينة، يا سيدتي تشي؟
The Prime Minister is a shrewd man.
رئيس الوزراء رجلٌ داهية.
I do not know of his intentions.
لا أعرف نواياه.
Zheng.
تشنغ.
If the law truly cannot tolerate him,
إذا كان القانون حقاً لا يتسامح معه،
I beg you, for the sake of your bond as uncle and nephew,
أرجوكم، من أجل الحفاظ على رابطة العم وابن أخيكم،
please leave his body intact.
أرجوكم اتركوا جثته سليمة.
The Flower-Crowned General has arrived.
لقد وصل الجنرال المتوج بالزهور.
[Qionghua]
[كيونغهوا]
Changyu.
تشانغيو.
How are you?
كيف حالك؟
How is your injury?
كيف حال إصابتك؟
I'm fine.
أنا بخير.
[Qionghua]
[كيونغهوا]
Come here.
تعال الى هنا.
Mother Consort.
الأم القرينة.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
Wei Yan has been captured.
تم القبض على وي يان.
My brother has gone dumb.
أخي أصبح غبياً.
The world has shifted.
لقد تغير العالم.
What's the point of you
ما الفائدة من وجودك؟
still hiding the truth?
هل ما زلت تخفي الحقيقة؟
The world has indeed shifted.
لقد تغير العالم بالفعل.
It has already shifted
لقد تغير بالفعل
17 years ago.
قبل 17 عاماً.
When Consort Virtue first entered the palace,
عندما دخلت كونسورت فيرتو القصر لأول مرة،
she was a very aloof person.
كانت شخصية منعزلة للغاية.
She never vied for His Majesty's favor.
لم تسعَ قط لنيل رضا جلالته.
[Late Emperor, Qi Yi]
[الإمبراطور الراحل تشي يي]
Then, she was found to be pregnant.
ثم تبين أنها حامل.
The month of pregnancy determined by the royal physician
شهر الحمل الذي يحدده الطبيب الملكي
did not match the records of the Department of State Affairs.
لم تتطابق مع سجلات وزارة شؤون الدولة.
Did Consort Virtue really have an affair with Wei Yan?
هل أقامت كونسورت فيرتو علاقة غرامية مع وي يان؟
Qi Rongyin was 3 months pregnant.
كانت تشي رونغين حاملاً في شهرها الثالث.
Counting back the days,
بالعودة إلى الوراء بالأيام،
she must have conceived it around the Mid-Autumn Festival.
لا بد أنها فكرت في الأمر في فترة عيد منتصف الخريف.
At the Mid-Autumn banquet that year,
في مأدبة منتصف الخريف في ذلك العام،
Wei Yan got drunk at the palace banquet.
سكر وي يان في مأدبة القصر.
He lost his propriety after drinking
فقد صوابه بعد شربه الكحول
and defiled a palace maid.
ودنس خادمة القصر.
Unfortunately, the Late Emperor and his officials caught him
لسوء الحظ، قبض عليه الإمبراطور الراحل ومسؤولوه
in the act on their way to admire the moon.
أثناء قيامهم بذلك في طريقهم للاستمتاع بمشاهدة القمر.
She was just a lowly palace maid,
كانت مجرد خادمة قصر متواضعة،
so the Late Emperor could not make a scene right there.
لذلك لم يتمكن الإمبراطور الراحل من إثارة ضجة هناك.
He simply bestowed that maid upon Wei Yan.
لقد منح تلك الخادمة ببساطة إلى وي يان.
The royal family is heartless.
العائلة المالكة عديمة الرحمة.
After Consort Virtue was found to be pregnant,
بعد أن تبين أن كونسورت فيرتو حامل،
she was interrogated every night.
كانت تخضع للاستجواب كل ليلة.
Until the night of the Laba Festival,
حتى ليلة مهرجان لابا،
when Qingyuan Palace suddenly caught fire...
عندما اشتعلت النيران فجأة في قصر تشينغ يوان...
Lord Wei? You.
سيد وي؟ أنت.
The Imperial Guard on patrol
الحرس الإمبراطوري في دورية
rushed to put out the fire,
سارعوا لإخماد الحريق،
[Qingyuan Palace]
[قصر تشينغيوان]
Only to discover that Wei Yan
ليكتشفوا أن وي يان
had entered the Capital without a decree
دخل العاصمة بدون مرسوم
and appeared in the Forbidden Palace.
وظهر في القصر المحرم.
Scram!
انصرف!
Zhao Xun once confessed
اعترف تشاو شون ذات مرة
that the palace fire was set by Crown Princess Chengde.
أن حريق القصر أشعلته ولية العهد الأميرة تشنغده.
Is there a hidden story behind this?
هل هناك قصة خفية وراء هذا؟
Have you ever seen water thrown into a fire
هل سبق لك أن رأيت الماء يُلقى في النار؟
make the flames leap even higher?
هل تجعل النيران تقفز أعلى؟
I have.
أملك.
That fire reeked of tung oil.
كانت رائحة زيت التونغ تفوح من تلك النار.
The palace city was besieged.
حوصرت المدينة التي كانت تضم القصر.
[Qingyuan Palace]
[قصر تشينغيوان]
The sounds of fighting shook the heavens.
هزت أصوات القتال السماء.
Just like the day before yesterday.
تماماً كما كان الحال قبل يومين.
Later, the attending royal physician committed suicide.
وفي وقت لاحق، انتحر الطبيب الملكي المعالج .
He left a suicide note saying
ترك رسالة انتحار يقول فيها
that Consort Virtue was never pregnant at all.
أن كونسورت فيرتو لم تكن حاملاً على الإطلاق.
So,
لذا،
the one who set the fire was Crown Princess Chengde,
كانت ولية العهد الأميرة تشنغده هي من أشعلت النار .
but the one who burned Consort Virtue to death
لكن الذي أحرق قرينة الفضيلة حتى الموت
was the Late Emperor.
كان الإمبراطور الراحل.
Thank you, Your Highness,
شكراً لك يا صاحب السمو.
for telling me about the past.
لأنكِ أخبرتني عن الماضي.
Jiuheng, are you here to see your uncle off?
جيوهينغ، هل أنت هنا لتوديع عمك؟
It's me. I've come to finish
أنا هنا. لقد جئت لأنهي الأمر.
that unfinished game of chess with you.
تلك اللعبة غير المكتملة من الشطرنج معك.
The brat's father, General Xie, died tragically in Jinzhou.
توفي والد الطفل، الجنرال شي، بشكل مأساوي في جينتشو.
Regarding what happened back then,
فيما يتعلق بما حدث آنذاك،
he is determined to get an answer.
إنه مصمم على الحصول على إجابة.
It was clearly the Late Emperor's setup.
كان ذلك بوضوح من تدبير الإمبراطور الراحل.
Why are you bearing the infamy for a lifetime instead?
لماذا تتحمل أنت العار طوال حياتك بدلاً من ذلك؟
What are you hoping to gain?
ما الذي تأمل في تحقيقه؟
I believe
أعتقد
this chess formation is most familiar to you.
هذا التشكيل الشطرنجي مألوف لديك على الأرجح.
Have you made up your mind?
هل حسمت أمرك؟
If not,
وإلا،
let me take another nap.
دعني آخذ قيلولة أخرى.
Yan.
نعم.
You're cheating.
أنت تغش.
You promised to use only 30% of your skill.
لقد وعدت باستخدام 30% فقط من مهاراتك.
But clearly,
لكن من الواضح،
you're going all out to corner me.
أنت تبذل قصارى جهدك لمحاصرتي.
I really am only using 30%.
أنا في الحقيقة لا أستخدم سوى 30%.
Then just admit that.
إذن اعترف بذلك فحسب.
I'm bad at chess
أنا سيء في الشطرنج
and can't beat you.
ولا يستطيع هزيمتك.
I'm done.
أنا انتهيت.
Fine. I'll make a different move.
حسناً. سأتخذ خطوة مختلفة.
Let me think about
دعني أفكر في الأمر
how to lose gracefully with 30% skill.
كيفية الخسارة بروح رياضية مع مهارة بنسبة 30%.
It's not hard to lose.
ليس من الصعب أن تخسر.
Let me help you, Brother.
دعني أساعدك يا ​​أخي.
Sister, stop messing around.
يا أختي، كفى عبثاً.
Brother, you blockhead.
يا أخي، يا غبي.
Win again, and you'll scare Sister-in-law away.
اربح مرة أخرى، وستخيف زوجة أخيك وتجعلها تبتعد.
Wan'er said you were playing chess here.
قال وانير إنك كنت تلعب الشطرنج هنا.
I thought I'd join in the fun.
فكرت أن أشارك في المرح.
No need for ceremony.
لا داعي للمراسم.
Sit. Please sit.
اجلس. من فضلك اجلس.
If a piece becomes isolated and helpless,
إذا أصبحت قطعة موسيقية معزولة وعاجزة،
you must quickly find a way to revitalize it.
يجب عليك إيجاد طريقة سريعة لإعادة تنشيطه.
Chess is like life.
الشطرنج يشبه الحياة.
One must sacrifice to gain.
لا بد من التضحية لتحقيق المكاسب.
Grand Tutor,
المعلم الكبير،
those were your words.
تلك كانت كلماتك.
At this point,
عند هذه النقطة،
stop speaking in riddles.
توقف عن التحدث بالألغاز.
I never believed
لم أصدق ذلك أبداً
that you planned the Jinzhou Massacre.
أنك خططت لمذبحة جينتشو.
But why did you return to the Capital so abruptly back then?
لكن لماذا عدت إلى العاصمة فجأة في ذلك الوقت؟
What exactly happened?
ما الذي حدث بالضبط؟
Do you remember the osmanthus wine banquet
هل تتذكر وليمة نبيذ الأوسمانثوس؟
at the Eastern Palace on New Year's Eve 18 years ago?
في القصر الشرقي ليلة رأس السنة قبل 18 عامًا؟
Grand Tutor,
المعلم الكبير،
you were there too.
كنتَ هناك أيضاً.
That night,
في تلك الليلة،
I was young and arrogant,
كنت شاباً ومتغطرساً،
and my words sowed the seeds of disaster.
وكلماتي زرعت بذور الكارثة.
[The 25th year of Taikang]
[السنة الخامسة والعشرون من تايكانغ]
Today is New Year's Eve.
اليوم هو ليلة رأس السنة.
I invited you all here
لقد دعوتكم جميعاً إلى هنا
to taste the Eastern Palace's homemade osmanthus wine.
لتذوق نبيذ الأوسمانثوس المصنوع منزلياً في القصر الشرقي.
Fine wine in winter,
نبيذ فاخر في الشتاء،
[Crown Prince Chengde, Qi Yuan]
[ولي العهد تشنغده، تشي يوان]
Paired with roasted venison,
يُقدّم مع لحم الغزال المشوي،
isn't it delightful?
أليس هذا رائعاً؟
[Libationer of the Imperial Academy, Li Xing] [Minister of the Two Ministries, Tao Yi]
[لي شينغ، مُقدّم القرابين في الأكاديمية الإمبراطورية] [تاو يي، وزير الوزارتين]
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
This osmanthus wine
هذا النبيذ المصنوع من زهر الأوسمانثوس
is incredibly fragrant.
رائحته عطرة للغاية.
[General Wei Yan] [General Protector Xie Linshan]
[الجنرال وي يان] [الحامي العام شيه لينشان]
It is truly a fine brew.
إنه مشروب رائع حقاً.
Here, Your Highness.
تفضل يا صاحب السمو.
Let me toast you again.
دعوني أرفع نخبكم مرة أخرى.
General Xie.
الجنرال شيه.
Did you get permission today
هل حصلت على الإذن اليوم؟
to drink to your heart's content?
أن تشرب حتى ترتوي؟
I advise you to drink less.
أنصحك بتقليل شرب الكحول.
Save some for the rest of us
وفر بعضاً لنا جميعاً
to have a taste, won't you?
لتذوقها، أليس كذلك؟
General Wei is right.
الجنرال وي محق.
Linshan, you have a high tolerance.
لينشان، لديك قدرة تحمل عالية.
If you don't restrain yourself,
إذا لم تكبح جماح نفسك،
there will be none left for us.
لن يبقى لنا شيء.
You...
أنت...
Grand Tutor,
المعلم الكبير،
it's just osmanthus wine.
إنه مجرد نبيذ الأوسمانثوس.
As long as you all like it,
طالما أنكم جميعًا تحبونه،
there is plenty.
يوجد الكثير.
Good.
جيد.
- Let's drink. - We'll have our share.
- هيا نشرب. - سنأخذ نصيبنا.
- Come on.
هيا بنا.
Fine wine, good food,
نبيذ فاخر، طعام جيد،
loyal subjects, a wise ruler,
رعايا مخلصون، حاكم حكيم،
and the company of close friends.
وصحبة الأصدقاء المقربين.
These are the greatest joys in life.
هذه هي أعظم أفراح الحياة.
Qilin, my friend.
كيلين، يا صديقي.
This might be the last time
قد تكون هذه هي المرة الأخيرة
we stay up for New Year's Eve together.
نسهر معًا ليلة رأس السنة.
[General Discipline Inspector, He Jingyuan]
[المفتش العام للانضباط، هي جينغ يوان]
I am about to leave the Capital
أنا على وشك مغادرة العاصمة
for Jinzhou.
لجينتشو.
[Huaihua General Wei Qilin]
[جنرال هوايهوا وي تشيلين]
He,
هو،
the Northwest Frontier is desolate.
الحدود الشمالية الغربية قاحلة.
Jinzhou, Chongzhou, and Jizhou are especially barren.
جينتشو وتشونغتشو وجيتشو قاحلة بشكل خاص.
You must take care of yourself on this trip.
يجب عليك أن تعتني بنفسك في هذه الرحلة.
A good man should establish himself.
ينبغي للرجل الصالح أن يثبت نفسه.
It is better than being in the Capital,
إنه أفضل من التواجد في العاصمة،
bowing and scraping to the powerful.
الانحناء والتملق للأقوياء.
What a pity.
يا للأسف.
I won't be there for my nephew's birth.
لن أكون حاضراً عند ولادة ابن أخي.
Niece.
ابنة الأخت.
You prefer daughters?
هل تفضل البنات؟
He, you're more well-read than I am.
أنت أكثر اطلاعاً مني.
Give your niece a name.
أعطي ابنة أختك اسماً.
Why don't you let your Lord name her?
لماذا لا تدع ربّك يسميها؟
General Wei's rank is too high.
رتبة الجنرال وي مرتفعة للغاية.
I fear the child can't bear such weight.
أخشى أن الطفل لا يستطيع تحمل هذا العبء.
Grand Libationer,
كبير مُحتفي المشروبات،
my Jiuheng is quite smart.
جيو هينغ خاصتي ذكي جداً.
When can he go to your Imperial Academy
متى يمكنه الالتحاق بأكاديميتك الإمبراطورية؟
to study?
للدراسة؟
Xie Zheng is still a child.
لا يزال شيه تشنغ طفلاً.
You are his uncle.
أنت عمه.
His own father isn't even anxious.
حتى والده ليس قلقاً.
Who says I'm not anxious?
من قال إني لست قلقاً؟
You have no idea.
ليس لديك أدنى فكرة.
That little rascal is a terror.
ذلك الوغد الصغير مرعب.
He causes trouble all day long.
إنه يسبب المشاكل طوال اليوم.
I'm not kidding.
أنا لا أمزح.
I want to send him to the Imperial Academy right now
أريد إرساله إلى الأكاديمية الإمبراطورية الآن
so you can discipline him properly.
حتى تتمكن من تأديبه بالشكل الصحيح.
Changyu.
تشانغيو.
Changyu?
تشانغيو؟
Yes.
نعم.
Wei Changyu.
وي تشانغيو.
"Chang," as in "Long may I stay by your side,"
"تشانغ"، كما في "أتمنى أن أبقى بجانبك طويلاً".
and "yu," as in "Where jade steps bloom with springtide."
و"يو"، كما في "حيث تتفتح درجات اليشم مع حلول الربيع".
What do you think?
ماذا تعتقد؟
That is a fine name.
إنه اسم جميل.
Later, I'll bring your niece to greet you.
لاحقاً، سأحضر ابنة أختك لتحيتك.
Good wine.
نبيذ جيد.
- Next year, General will lead troops to guard Jinzhou. - Good wine.
- في العام المقبل، سيقود الجنرال القوات لحراسة جينتشو. - نبيذ جيد.
If the General does not object,
إذا لم يعترض الجنرال،
I wish to go with you...
أرغب في الذهاب معك...
And face the national crisis together.
ولنواجه الأزمة الوطنية معاً.
Your Highness's safety
سلامة سموكم
concerns the stability of the court and the state.
يتعلق الأمر باستقرار المحكمة والدولة.
We cannot be rash.
لا يمكننا أن نكون متسرعين.
Indeed.
بالفعل.
A noble son must not sit under a leaky roof.
لا يجوز لابن نبيل أن يجلس تحت سقف مثقوب.
Please reconsider, Your Highness.
أرجو إعادة النظر في الأمر يا صاحب السمو.
There is something you do not know.
هناك شيء لا تعرفه.
There were floods in the south this summer.
شهد الجنوب فيضانات هذا الصيف.
I went to provide disaster relief.
ذهبت لتقديم الإغاثة في حالات الكوارث.
But the Jia family obstructed me at every turn.
لكن عائلة جيا عرقلتني في كل منعطف.
The victims suffered unspeakably.
لقد عانى الضحايا معاناة لا توصف.
My father was furious.
كان والدي غاضباً جداً.
But he did not pursue
لكنه لم يتابع الأمر
the faults of the Sixteenth Prince and the Jia family.
أخطاء الأمير السادس عشر وعائلة جيا.
Instead, he blamed me
بل ألقى اللوم عليّ
for ineffective relief efforts.
بسبب جهود الإغاثة غير الفعالة.
Over these years,
على مدى هذه السنوات،
Father has been especially harsh on me,
كان والدي قاسياً جداً معي،
while being more than lenient towards the Jia family
مع إظهار تسامح كبير تجاه عائلة جيا
and the Sixteenth Prince.
والأمير السادس عشر.
I am lost.
أنا تائه.
Perhaps,
ربما،
only by staying away from the court
فقط بالابتعاد عن المحكمة
and achieving merit at the border
وتحقيق الجدارة على الحدود
can I find
هل يمكنني أن أجد
my ultimate path.
مساري النهائي.
These family trifles...
هذه الأمور العائلية البسيطة...
I have made a fool of myself
لقد جعلت نفسي أضحوكة
in front of you all.
أمامكم جميعاً.
Your Highness, you possess both benevolence and virtue.
يا صاحب السمو، أنت تمتلك كلاً من الكرم والفضيلة.
You are wise and brave.
أنت حكيم وشجاع.
You are the only choice to succeed to the throne.
أنت الخيار الوحيد لخلافة العرش.
I just don't understand
أنا لا أفهم
why His Majesty is so biased.
لماذا جلالته متحيز إلى هذا الحد؟
If the Emperor lacks virtue,
إذا كان الإمبراطور يفتقر إلى الفضيلة،
then simply have him abdicate.
ثم ببساطة اجعله يتنازل عن العرش.